Noel Phyllis Birkby Papers, 1932-1994
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Man working on a lathe. More of the cement chimes or bells, different from film 13 - beautiful - hung on strings. Another set of them, different kind.
Film in good shape, no scratches, well exposed. Ceiling w/red in between the cement rafters. Open space w/cement between, makes it look very light. More hanging bells in a new configuration. Spikes of the building.
Now in a car. She's in back seat, so we see driver's face in rearview mirror, and a woman sitting next to driver. Now beautiful abstract shot CU of rearview mirror which is reflecting natural scenes as car goes forward. Blurred countryside. Back to Canyonlands [see film 134]. She must have visited this place first and then gone on this trip.
15. SOLERI.
Flintstones comic of construction in desert setting similar to redrock.
16. SPACE CENTER ASSEMBLY BUILDING. color
Shots of trees and roadside moving past with Space Center Assembly Building in background. Unexposed strip. Driving onto center grounds; stopped at a guard booth. Descending upon the building, driving closer. Shot of building out window of car. Interior of building--greenish, a sign says "cell 3--cell 4." Interior shots, of structural elements, start close up, zoom out. Also panning across room. Shot of glass wall. Wide shot of hanger (?), workers walking past. close up of sign: "hard hat area." Wide shot of ceiling and track lighting glowing greenly. Another pan across the glass wall. Dark interior shots. More pans up and down the glass wall, in succession. Jump cuts between shots of darkly exposed interior. Shot of backlit interior structure: beams, supports. More zooms and pans through the interior. Med. shot of missile, panning it up and down. Jump cuts of between sticker of American flag, group walking out, interior of mission control. Interior landscape shot. Airstrip? Jump cuts of shots of mission control. Close up of digital counter.
17. "WATERSIDE SITE/YALE SHOTS". Overexposed.
Shot from a car driving by Yale U. When she gets to Yale, nicely shot architectural studies, all of different buildings. Window details, roof details. Good shape, no scratches. Only drive part is overexposed.
ART FILMS
18. "A&P BROOME ST./ICE SKATE". 1962 1.5 min. on Market St. at night. 1.5 min. ice skating in the country.
Night shooting of store fronts and signs. DeSantis Prime Meats in bright red. Chubby's Restaurant. Daytime, looks like near her home in Chinatown. Maybe her street. Bridge or subway trestles. She's shooting out of her loft window at people walking by on the street. Store was across the street.
Second part - Man w/mustache ice skating. Person in yellow rainhat. Snow on ground. Old-fashioned ice skate - close up of. Another guy ice skating. Abstract study of ice. Would be beautiful projected. Shooting television set. Rowan and Martin's Laugh-In, Goldie Hawn, etc.
19. "A&P" MARKET ST. 8/6/60. 8 mm color, Overexposed.
Across the street from her home.
20. "ANN AND SUE. SUMMER 1970. Color Sup. 8.
Sweet little study. Interesting architectural house on ocean at the beach. A woman waving from the stairs. Looks like Long Island. Woman lying in the sand, CU of another woman reading Novel Perspectives. Two women, Ann and Sue, in the sand together, CU of their feet crossed, touching. Good exposure. Lot of foot study. Slightly scratched. Still feet. Major feet study, more feet. CU of one of them. Medium shot of same rolling in the sand and out of the picture. Same woman by the ocean.
21. "AUTO SHOW".
Perfect condition, details and features of cars in an auto show. Beautifully shot for design and light. Alfa-Romeo, Ferrari Spitfire, Land Rover, Austin Healey.
22. BACKYARD 1979. 8 mm. color.
Looks like an urban backyard - TV antenna, clothes on lines. Probably shot from her living space, out window. It's a pun on backyard, potted plants and laundry and other buildings directly facing your own. Footage is good, slightly green. Manhattan skyscrapers shot sideways, city hall as well as vertical. Nice shot of white laundry, with city hall in background. Looks like a creative piece. 1979. Potted plants. Slightly scratched. A lot of cables and ropes, beautifully shot, great color, pulleys. Looks like boat mast, ropes and pulleys, it is. River is right there in back yard.
23. "BACKYARD". Approx. 5 min. (color)
Fairly dark exposures: Shot of NYC skyline. Shots of buildings. Shots of buildings out of focus, focusing. Shot of side of building taken through a window; pans up through frame. shot of twilight sky, fading light. Jump cuts between quick shots of buildings, TV antenna.
24. "BEACH". (color)
Close up of women's faces. Side close up of woman's face, she's driving. Series of close ups and extreme close ups of female faces, possibly inside car. Close up of a woman's neck, mouth in side profile. Arrival at the beach: 3 women walk into the frame, into the distance. Shot of hazy beach. Med. long shot of woman holding shark skeleton up to the camera. Another woman spreads a blanket. Another walks away to a dune. Med. shot of reclining woman's midsection from back. Jump cut to front shot. Close up of woman's face. Another woman's face. Splice. Shot of three women running away from the camera toward the water. One woman runs back and forth along the shoreline. Two women link arms and twirl around. Woman in bikini stands dead shark upright in sand. Shot of woman in the bikini and woman in yellow shirt jesting with each other. Wide shot of women standing with backs to camera, looking at the water. More shots of goofing around. Wide shots of women walking, running down the beach. The woman in red walks toward the camera, into an extreme close up. Splice. Med. shot of dunes. Shot of woman sitting on the dunes. More shots of the woman on the dunes from various angles. Med. long shot of two women cuddling. More shots of women on dunes: walking around, linking arms. Pan across dunes to shoreline. Long shot of woman walking over dune toward camera. Stops, lies down, disappears, sits up again. Rear long shots of women at shoreline, looking out at water.
25. "BEACH--FOOTPRINTS. FLOTSAM 8/66. 8 mm. color
Woman at beach w/dog. Wonderful third shot of two foot prints in sand merged. Exposure good, color good. First part of first shot in leader is damaged. Footprints in the sand. Ocean. Shot footprints so they look 3-dimensional in bas relief in shadow on them. Small doll in seaweed, flotsam, washed up by the waves. Coughdrops in seaweed. Interesting junk in seaweed. Then a lone sandal. A milk carton, etc. Dead bird. Sea grasses.
26. BEACH HOUSE, 7/69. 8mm Color.
All pink cast. Just flotsam, crabs, rocks. Do not see a beach house at all. Sand is pink, water is pink. Skeleton. Sailboat. A face of Louise Fishman. Overexposed Louise F. in pink water. Not worth much.
27. "BEACH WALK, B.H.?. BEACH WALK. Short Roll, Super 8, 2 min.
Possibly Barbara Hammer. Back of woman walking, running at beach. Ocean.
28. "BEACH W/DOGS--SAGAPONACK.
Woman w/afghan dog, running by beach. Woman sunning. CUs of different women sunning and dogs, more dogs, different dogs, CUs of their dog hair, interesting texture of CUs. Many minutes. CU of woman's laughing face. Goggles in the sun. Doghair w/ocean behind. Face of the Afghan. Tail of Afghan. Japanese multi-colored umbrellas, creatively shot piece. Two dogs sniffing each other. Scottish terrier. Women playing frisbee. Slightly scratched, good exposure
29. "BICI'S DIVORCE". B&W Super 8
Bici [Forbes] on one side, line separates paper, other side says Jeff [Hendricks, Fluxus artist]. Seems to be pasted on a wall in a house w/barbed wire between, in interior of a home. Zoom on a person but dark, can't tell who it is. Maybe Jeff. Woman - also dark footage. Tangle of barbed wire w/somebody's hands touching it. Looks like a divorce ritual. Woman enmeshing herself in barbed wire. Dark. Door w/light bulb hanging by and a bouquet of flowers. Something wrapped in bubble wrap.
30. "BMT [Brooklyn Mass Transit]//BRIDGE". B&W Super 8. 3 minutes.
Shot at night. Looks like white lights in a dark space. Probably a subway car going by. Probably would look good projected. She lived under the Manhattan Bridge. Would like to see it projected. Pristine condition. Five shots of Louise Fishman and another woman at the beach picking up shells.
31. "CITY ISLAND WOMEN". Super 8 color. 8/71.
Mannequin of a woman's head then cuts to a woman in the street. CUs of women in street walking by. No scratches, good color. Policewoman, all different ages of women, gray haired, long brown hair. Women sitting down, studying, Playboy bunny in B&W. Drawing of a woman w/mustache on her. Interior shots. Shot of Phyllis w/aviator glasses and hair pulled back. Shots of a man and other women, CUs. Probably an architectural group. CUs of hands slicing wood, building models. A photo or postcard of Psyche kissing a woman, statue of woman's head looking down, infant sucking breast on statue. Photo of two women who look like mother and sister or sisters, ancient photo. Photo of two women w/shawls, sign that says SISTERS. Looks like a photographic show of sisters.
Exterior shot of a blonde woman CU. Long shot of her as she turns head and looks at traffic. Shot of another woman very tan and also slightly blonde and smiling towards camera. Shot of water w/sailboat on it. Might be Catalina or ?
Back to same woman, lying down, CU of her face w/hand shading her eyes, smiling, laughing, good shot but intermittent scratch but much of it not scratched. Feels very intimate.
32. "CLARK FEREBEE HOUSE.. Color. Super 8
Trees on the beach. Brief shot of a man walking. House, wood shingle, wood patterns, light on wood, graphic shooting of shingles. Probably Clark at the beach. Tractor at the beach. Clark in rearview mirror of tractor and driving it on the sand at the beach and it's some dirt shovel or tractor. Only thing on the house is the shingles.
33. "CLARK/FEREBEE, PIGEONS NEAR MACY'S". 8 mm color, 5/70
Trees, bay window reflecting the ocean, more flotsam, junk floating in the water. Pigeons near Macy's in second part. Statue in the Macy's area. People dining outdoors. Good focus, not scratched. Large red X sculpture w/pigeons and people dining around it. Lots of pigeons being fed and statue of man w/NY buildings behind it. Maybe Herald Square.
34. DOGS.
Two German Shepherds playing in hallway. Interesting brown tones. Night footage, distant lights. Back to dogs again in living room. Colors nice, playful, fill up most of frame. Person wearing a Samuel Gompers sweatshirt in picture, a guy, seems to be his dog. Out the window dark again back again, out the window.
35. "DRIVE. (color)
Shots of driving down twisting country roads in winter. A bit of snow is on the ground. Shot through the windshield. Camera is very jumpy. Shots of driving through country roads through rain globules on the windshield. The rain has turned to ice. Quick shots of passing cars. The ice has melted, blurring the windshield. Leader. Medium shots of the roadside, the camera is being moved back and forth. More shots of driving down country roads through windshield, but camera is zoomed in slightly on road. Shaking camera shots of same: roadside, trees, snow. Camera straightens out to stretch of road again. Windshield wipers pass across screen. The corner of the windshield appears in the frame. More winding roads. No more rain or snow.
36. FANTASY FILM, DREAM FORBES, BIRKBY, NAOMI FATT.- print, not original.
Some hand colored footage. In a violet scene she cuts from B&W to color and then back. Does that several times and intercuts a woman's breast being revealed w/ a man's glaring eyes. Hands on breasts, cut to man's eyes. Violet scene seems to be two women in sexual wrestling intercut w/men looking and w/ the breast. The woman is looking back. Two men behind table watching. Men in sepia. Women in color, rolling on the floor. Circle vignette around two men, cut to a circle mirror of the breast, cut to circle of two women, black all around, hole in balloon. Her creative work.
37. "FIBISHES" 11/68, FALL FOLIAGE FAMILY. Reg. 8
Dark. Nature footage, man shot like an hour before sunset, footage looks reddish. CU of a woman. Man and woman at the seaside. Beautifully lit little kid going up a small hillock with the light catching her orange jacket. Everything dark but the orange jacket. Everything dark but the orange light of a person's face. Kid being held by a person. Wildweeds.
Perfect exposure of a fall day on second half. Child in fall colored coat surrounded by beautiful fall foliage. Mom in bellbottoms walks up tree limb barefoot while child looks. Yellow-leafed trees around. Kid follows in foliage colored jacket. Out of focus trees. Another woman below looks up at beautiful red-leaved tree. Lake w/fall trees around. Beautiful two leaves floating in water w/lily pads. Dock into water w/two women and a child. More foliage relfected in the water. Footage is in good condition.
38. FLOWERS STAMFORD. Color, 1 min.
Various short shots of flowers. Good shape.
39. "FRANCES, WATER, ETC. @ LYNDA'S [SIMMONS].,
Frances Doughty--one good shot at head of roll; rest water reflections, leaves, sunlight; another woman soft focus, Lynda?
40. "HEAD CHANGE.. 5 min. 16 mm. color sound film. Completed work.
Love obsession w/woman named Leslie [Ena whom she met at WSPA?] with whom she ran WSPA conferences with. Shot from slides and television footage. Slide of Phyllis w/long hair, halfway through. Soundtrack is popular song "She's That Kind Of Woman" sung by Jade and Sassaparilla. [Ena] Leslie? gets her hair cut. Not dated. Tech. advisor Alida Walsh. In can and mailing carton.
41. "HEAD CHANGE. 16mm. elements film, AB roll, 16 mm. magrack for "Head Change."
42. Slide outtakes from "Head Change".. 16mm
43. Video outtakes from "Head Change". color 16 mm., 30 seconds.
44. "Head Change.
Original footage that was optically printed, 16 mm. of photographs and slides. The WSPA, of Phyllis that were used in Head Change.
45. Outtakes from "Head Change". 16 mm.
red filter used on slides used in Head Change. Video footage. Slides of haircut. Slides of WSPA group.
46. Title roll for "Head Change".. 16mm
47. More outtakes, slides from "Head Change".. 16mm
48. Titles for "Head Change".. 16mm
52. Extra video for "Head Change".. 16mm
53. More titles for "Head Change".. 16mm
54. "KITE" aka GETTING IT UP. Super 8, 15 minutes. Print.
Sweet Film. Two women lovers at the beach flying kites, lying in sand, holding hands. Nice close ups of sandy levi crotch; shoes with sand, (showing two women together). Kite abstracted to form. Orange and black on white beach. 4 women. One with camera. All in same kite scene. Shot of Phyllis, CU. With aviator clear glasses, eyes closed, throws her head back. CU of Phyllis's face with someone else's fingers in her mouth (or her own). Nice CU's of P.B. Group shots with women and kite. Medium CU of tying kite. Kite flying. Phyllis and others in same shot watch kite. Phyllis holding kite string looks at Louise Fishman? Passing string back and forth. Phyllis with hands up as if lost kite.
55. "KITE" 11/19/71. Sup. 8. Original
56. LONE WOMAN ON BEACH 5/70. Overexposed Reg. 8,
Woman on the beach 5/70. At very end, woman walks away down beach, good exposure. Shots of ocean.
57. LOUISE FISHMAN AT THE BEACH. One and one-half minutes.
Paper spliced. Do not project until splice repaired. Nice creative shooting of two women at the beach, shooting from behind, she shot in a way that they jump from side to side. Image in good shape.
58. LOVE LETTER. 16mm
Pan down a slide of Phyllis to a life size outline drawing of her body. Second shot of drawing, inside body are written things, in the head a fried egg with tears dripping from it and a smile and it said around the outside "a new head." Second shot of legs w/bellbottoms. Left leg says "say acting drawing speaking" right legs says "do something working hearing." One leg says pain one leg says love. Drawing of another person in the class. Dissolve from one figure into another. Could be same person, two different drawings. A slide of one woman, Leslie maybe, different one than we've seen. Three or four photos of another woman, shots short so that they're animated. Looks like Leslie? Graphic like a computer printout Phyllis imprinted over the slide of another woman. Completed film.
59. MIME. Workprint, Super 8, 2 min. (Tails Out)
60. MISCELLANEOUS.
First shot of a woman's hand by a yellow structure. Shot mostly from a TV screen, possibly. Second part - an outake from "Tractor." Do not project, paper splice. Not very interesting.
61. NUDE MAN AT BEACH.
Man w/sunglasses CU. Woman w/sunglasses CU. Extreme CUs showing eyepiece, creatively shot, mouth, nose, camera turned. Long shots of people around a swimming pool in LA. Creekwater, dim shot of a man sitting on a rock in a cave, actually not so bad. Then in another position, doing a shoulder stand on same rock and water going around. Now he's nude. She zooms in on his penis and now there's a rear shot. Another nude shot of him lounging on the rocks. At the beach and same man is lying in sand nude between rocks, kind of crawling on hands and knees as if coming out of the ocean. Another shot of him walking into this cave. CUs of him w/sky behind. Ocean looks Carribean. Ocean is turquoise. CU of him, has a beard. Woman at the beach holding up seeds from a tree or something. Same woman w/camera and looks like her hands are on her bra? or underwear?
62. ROOFTOP SHOOTING. 1.5 minutes
Good shape, nicely exposed. Texaco station at night. New York(?) rooftop, water towers. Could be shot from her roof. Store that says Ernest Chandler's Goods, Tarpaulins, Tents and Bags on its brick building side. Circular pan shot, light is nice, last hour of the day. Manhattan bridge in background, or Brooklyn behind the projects. Next day, Texaco sign in daylight.
63. SCENERY. Super 8, Color, 1972. 1 minute.
A few miscellaneous shots of trees.
64. SEASHELLS BY THE SEASHORE. Super 8, color, 3 minutes.
Carribean or South Seas or ?.
65. SHIRLEY WALTON. Super 8. Black/White. Approx. 12 min.
Unedited footage gets good at end. Mostly dark, too dark to read. Woman in doorway or room posing. Sections of patterned cloth and woman lying down. Has hands crossed on stomach, zoom out, she appears to be pregnant. CU of woman's face without glasses. Nude, swollen breasts, she is pregnant! Beautiful nude long shot, well exposed of pregnant Shirley in interior. Shirley poses erotically while pregnant! Holds stomach. Tummy full frame. Zoom out to LS frontal, side, other side. Same shot from behind. Series of hands on tummy. Shirley dancing? and sitting.
66. "STAMFORD. LONG ISLAND BEACH.. B&W. Reg. 8.
Long Island beaches, has drift fences. Group of men and women on the beach, CUs. She's shooting the way the fences keep at the sand. Looks like Long Island. CU of smiling face of either Ann or Sue, refers back to Beachhouse Film #20?. Beach grasses. Ocean and another woman at the beach. Sue? Hand holding up a rock w/piece of seaweed growing out of it. Hand and foot, hand is going through seaweed, shot from one side of the frame and then the other. A toy cow on the beach.
67. "STAMFORD" II. 8/68 8 mm.
Red and White sailboat. She shoots it very expressively w/graphic design using the shape and color of the sails for a design pattern in part.
67A. STAMFORD.
Ocean, sailboat being set up, Sunfish sailboat on the beach. Red and white sail. Not scratched. Woman and child looking for seashells. Lots of the boat putting out to sea. Man and woman in boat. Hulls of boats on racks. Sunfish sailing. Don't know who people are. Older heterosexual couple.
68. "Sun on Water, Sky, Rough Cut(?). BEACH SUNSET.
Shots of ocean, sunset, ocean, beach foam, foam on sand, lot of soft focus. Waves coming in and out at sunset. Nice cloud shots. Sunset behind clouds. Quite beautiful. Film has a big scratch in it. Looks like she shot a sunset in real time. That's the end of it.
69. "TRACTOR". Original.
70. "TRACTOR". Super 8, color print, approx. 4-5 min.
This is an edited completed Super 8 Film titled TRACTOR. Good Condition. Completed: 11/19/1971 by Noel Phyllis Birkby. The tractor woman is Frederica Leser.
Shots of woman driving tiny tractor. Scenery shots of background. Slightly overexposed. Camera point of view of ground; dark shot of woman driving towards you. Side shot through bushes of woman driving. Frame through interior of home window zoom to tractor. Second shot through corner of barn? window. Side ways with camera turned to the side! of woman driving. Upside down shot of woman driving. Series of camera turned sideways or upside down. Afghan hound CU. Short shots of side ways, upside down. Tractor is mowing lawn. (I remember Phyllis telling me about this film. She considered it complete and a work in itself which it is.) Sunset shots.
71. "TWO BRIDGES".
Brooklyn Bridge, beautifully shot, some scratches, some perfect. The Golden Hour, hour before sunset. East River and buildings around the bridge. Last part is overexposed. Very last is good exposure again.
72. 2 BRIDGES MANHATTAN. Reg. 8, color.
Good color. Shot from rooftop. Rather beautiful. Some light flares. Car Carey's in. Crowds gathered on New York sidewalk. Shots from down in the crowd. Tuba and woman in red, white and blue dress, back to camera, turns. Shots from behind stage. Man in suit turns toward the camera. Men's handshakes w/mens suits. Carey shaking hands, CU of hands. Carey from stage w/microphone. Crowd shots very good. Wonderful character shots of crowd members. A lot of gesturing by Carey, hand gesturing. Series of his hands in frame. Color good, looks great.
73. "TWO BRIDGES ________. NEIGHBORHOOD/MANHATTAN BRIDGE. 1969
Half is black. Her location where she lived. Date of '69 on film. Market Street - One Way. Manhattan Bridge. Beautiful sepia cast to the film. Architectural details of railing. Sign - Community Control is Beautiful and Workable. Sign in Chinese. A shot of the anchorage of the Manhattan bridge. Film is not scratched. Street lights, a shot underneath the subway or bridge looking up. Long shot of Manhattan Bridge with the towers. Architectural details of cement. Snow on fences. Bridge scene through houses. Bridge scene from sidewalk w/community members, different ethnic groups. Then she shoots an abstract, may be the bridge, then darker buildings and a building where bridge was. Sign - Mobilization For Youth. Sign in Hebrew - 22 Rutgers Street. Jewish Daily Forward, huge sign. Important Lower East side footage. Sign - Lower East Side Information Servicecenter. Great roll. Beautiful shots of everything. Snow on trees, camera steady, people walking by. Incredibly beautiful.
74. UNTITLED. Approx. 3 minutes (color)
Darkly exposed shots of woman; zoom in on her face. Woman balances vase on her head. Woman sits with vase in front of her. Close up of her face, she's saying something, and blocks the camera with her hand. Camera zooms out. Another person surprises her by joining her. They bat at each other, then stand together at end.
75. WASHINGTON SQUARE PARK. Sup. 8, good condition, color, one minor scratch. Well exposed.
People in the park, in the arch, crowd gathered below arch. Kids in costume - Halloween? Lots of kids in costume below arch, walking, nicely shot.
Woman in clown costume. Kid w/great orange mask as devil, devil's tail, all by himself. A fake plant. CU of kid's face with paint smudges. Kid wrapped in white swaddling and turban. Crowd shots of kids and adults. In a playground section of park w/ropes, kids climbing ropes. Spinning platform. Football game. Seems to be just people in the park, documentation of how people use the park, that's what she'd be interested in. Dark footage. Hare Krishnas - well exposed. Hare Krishnas chanting, dancing w/signs. People using the park. That's it.
76. WASHINGTON SQUARE PARK.